[Music]
and we are live
everyone welcome to episode one of
ask abhijit it's great to see you all
thank you for being here
and before i begin i would like to
express my gratitude to all of you for
your support i've been a very reluctant
youtuber thus far i have made like three
videos in two years
but you have all been uh subscribing and
supporting me and
giving amazing comments so i would like
to thank you all from the bottom of my
art
of my heart i truly appreciate
your support so i have decided to
um i have a bunch of questions that you
have already asked me
uh ask abhijit i've got about
more than 600 questions thus far so i'm
going to answer a few of these
i won't be able to answer all of them
but i'll try my best to answer as many
as i can
so i will first answer some questions
that you have already asked and
later i will take some live questions as
well
so that's the format that i'm going to
follow today so
let's begin with question number one
and the question one is is it
true that there was no concept of india
or one nation before our independence
and india was just divided into many
kingdoms that would keep
fighting each other for example the
rajputs
so it's a good question
is india was india a nation in the past
no india was not a nation
the concept of nation and nation state
is a very new concept it's just 300
years old approximately three or four
hundred
hundred years old india has always been
a civilization
so there's a vast difference between a
civilization
and a nation a nation is a small or
large geographical entity
that is sovereign a civilization is much
bigger than that a civilization has a
common culture
it can have numerous smaller nations
within it
and yet it is one single entity
so that's what india has always been at
times india has been
unified under a single empire for
example the mauryan empire
the gupta empire shivaji's
empire tanishka's empire etc so
there were times when india was
completely unified and its geographical
extent went
much more than the current political
boundaries of india
and there were times when india was a
bunch of fragmented
kingdoms and it was still one single
civilization
so india has always been something
greater than a nation
india has always been a civilization so
before
india's independence in 1947 india was a
civilization
in 1947 what happened is that india
became
a nation-state and that to a truncated
one
so 1947 was a watershed in india's
history it became
diminished from a civilization to a
nation so historically india has been a
civilization
now yes india's uh kingdoms would fight
each other from time to time
it wasn't always the case whenever you
had a number of kingdoms there would be
inter kingdom rivalries for sure and
when you would have
a large empire under one single emperor
then there would be no such rivalries
so history is a cyclical process and
that's what india has seen because
india's history is so
so ancient india has thousands of years
of history so you see these cycles over
and over
this is talking historical cycles you
had empires you had kingdoms you had the
mahajanapadas there
the great republic states and so on so
that is the answer
india has always been a civilization a
nation is something that is
much smaller in scope than a
civilization
so today india is diminished it is a
nation
and one would aspire that india should
be a civilization
civilization again a civilization state
so hopefully that's something that will
happen in the future
but as of now india as a nation
historically it's always been a
civilization
despite having so many different
languages and so many local
manifestations
of this single unifying culture
so that's the answer to the question
it's a great question
let's go to question number two
so this is by hardik bhagti
can you explain about the battle forth
between alexander
and porus the battle of hidaspis was
king porus a descendant of the puru
dynasty why is there no indian textual
evidence of this great question again
so whenever you have a conflict between
two sides
between two parties or two nations or
two cultures
then in order to get a good
understanding of what truly happened
it behooves historians to look at what
both sides have to say about it so the
history that we are taught today
is of alexander's invasion of india he
was a great king he conquered everything
he came to india and he defeated this
great
brave king porus and then his soldiers
rebelled against him
and they said that we are very tired we
have been away from home for so many
years
we want to go back and so alexander
acquires
to the demands of his army and that's
why he went back
but he was victorious in india and he
could have gone further ahead if you
wish to
so this is the history this is the
narrative that
is taught to us and this is an entirely
greek narrative
this is what the greek historians have
written about alexander and his
uh supposed conquest of india
the strange thing is that indian sources
from that time
are completely silent about alexander
they do not mention alexander at all
which is very strange isn't it if such a
great conqueror came to
india's western doorstep then
how come there is no indian mention of
this great
invader alexander and this battle
of the uh which is supposed to have
happened uh at the banks of the river
jalam
this battle happened in punjab in in the
sindhu region and the strange thing is
that one of india's greatest
universities of all time takshashila
also happened to be in punjab which is
right next door essentially
to the site of the battle and
this is one of the greatest universities
of all time you had so many professors
of all kinds of different subjects
including current affairs political
science history
science and what not so if such an
enormous
and momentous battle happened right next
door to taksha sheila
how come none of india's scholars
recorded this event and wrote some
commentary or some sort of
uh you know some sort of record about it
how come there is no record of this
battle at all
and how come there is no record of
alexander at all and how come there is
no indian record of this king called
porus
why is that so and the strange thing is
that after alexander died
his general seleucus nicator became the
overall
king of the greeks and he again tried to
invade india and he entered eventually
into an alliance with our emperor
chandragupta maurya
so indian records mentioned seleucus
niketa extensively
and seleucus niketa is is the king who
comes right after alexander
so it's just a question of a decade or
so and yet there is no mention of
alexander in indian sources
so if one were to take this logically it
it would indicate
that indian sources and indian
historians and indian
and the indians of that time either did
not take any notice of alexander
or they considered him to be not worthy
of
writing about which would essentially
tell you that his
invasion was no big deal and it would
essentially tell you that
this king porus that he supposed
supposed to have defeated
must have been a very small king of some
western
outpost of india's boundary with persia
a so the greeks talk about porous like
he was some great
king who had a vast kingdom but there is
no mention of porus in indian texts
and so it would indicate that he was a
minor king
a minor chieftain of a border outpost of
india
so the fact that there is no
mention of alexander or porus at all in
indian sources
would indicate that the story is very
different from what the greeks have told
us
and that's the story that we we
learn about in our textbooks worldwide
including in india
so the russian martial the great russian
marshal
zukov who was one of the russia's great
military strategists
wrote about this and he said that what
really happened was that alexander
probably
lost to this minor border chieftain
porus
and the greek sources later embellished
the story and
invented a story of alexander defeating
porus and being forced back by the
actions of his own soldiers so i
i wonder why indian historians have
never taken up this angle they have just
blindly imbibed whatever the greek
historians have written about and
whatever the western historians write
about
so i think it is time to look at india's
history afresh
because the story doesn't quite add up
when it comes to alexander's
supposed invasion of india what i
believe happened is that he
came to western india he tried to invade
india he had this ambition of invading
india
he ran into a small border chieftain and
because this guy had elephants and
all that that's why i believe that
alexander suffered a defeat
in this skirmish with the indian king
and
we know that his horse died in this
battle and it is
most likely that alexander also got
grievously injured
in this battle with the indians and he
had to go back to babylon where he
died so i think that is the
is what really transpired we should
not believe the greek sources
blindly because it is well known that
greek sources have been
known to embellish and invent history
herodotus the father of history the
supposed father of history
is known to have invented fictitious
lands and fictitious people
people with three heads and people with
three eyes and what not
and this is accepted as history today
somehow so it is time to revisit
the history of india and revisit it from
our
own eyes and our own perspective so that
is what i really believe
transpired when it comes to alexander's
supposed invasion of india i think he
suffered
a calamitous loss in india and it
eventually led to his death
so good question the next question
is can there be possibilities of life
existing without
oxygen and is it also possible that many
planets have living organisms so
yes it is definitely possible for life
to exist without
oxygen if you look at the early history
of our own planet
then before if you go back to before
about two billion two and a half billion
years
before the present then there was almost
no oxygen in our atmosphere and yet we
had life
and what happened was that there was
this kind of the species of bacteria
called cyanobacteria that developed the
that evolved and developed the the
ability to
do photosynthesis which means that they
were able to create energy out of
sunlight
and the outcome of photosynthesis the
outcome of the output of that reaction
is oxygen so gradually these bacteria
started producing
oxygen in the atmosphere that oxygen was
released in the atmosphere
and that's how the earth slowly became
oxygenated and
once it crossed a certain threshold it
led to a mass uh extinction
of a lot of the species that were on
earth because at that time
oxygen was actually poisonous to most of
the species on our planet
so this is called the great oxygen
disaster the great oxidation catastrophe
or the oxygen holocaust you can look it
up or the information is available
online
so yes our own planet harbored life
which survived without oxygen and for
whom oxygen was actually a poison
so there are lots of different
biochemistries
of life that that uh support life
without the presence of oxygen
so so that's what we had on our planet
as well so yes
life is definitely possible without
oxygen
now to the second part of the question
is it possible that many planets have
living organisms
definitely i think that there could be
microbial life
inside our own solar system itself
because
there we know that there is water on
certain moons around jupiter and saturn
and there are lots of uh hydrocarbons
there's the presence of
organic hydrocarbons that are supportive
that
that form the building blocks of life on
earth
these uh hydrocarbons i are found on
comets on meteorites and on many of
these moons
of jupiter and saturn and there are
moons that have subsurface
oceans uh europa is one example
enceladus i believe ganymede and titan
the moon of
saturn also has very interesting
chemistry and it has a very thick
atmosphere
so i believe and even mars i mean we
know that mars was once a very
wet planet and we know that there is
water below the surface in mars and
sometimes you even see water flowing on
the surface of mars
so there is definitely the potential for
microbial life microorganisms
on mars and on these various other moons
of our own solar system
so i believe it's quite likely that
there could be life
inside our own solar system outside of
earth
so that's the first thing and i think
that life in this form could exist in
abundance across our galaxy
and across the universe and i am pretty
much
certain that there should be intelligent
life as well
intelligence that is on par with our
intelligence or maybe it even exceeds
our intelligence
we have so many stars in our own galaxy
i think approximately 400 billion stars
and we know that planets are very common
almost every star system that we know of
has been found to have at least a couple
of planets
and there are bill i would say there are
trillions of galaxies in the observable
universe
so if you add that all up there are so
many planets and so many possibilities
of life
and i would say that the odds are that
they that intelligent life should also
be quite common
in the universe so yes i believe i'm i'm
pretty sure
that life exists outside our planet and
even intelligent life may exist
so that's the answer to this question
next question
can you please this is sunny nagi can
you please explain what is the higgs
boson particle and what's the higgs
field
right so the best theory of
of physics that we have thus far is
called quantum field theory
so according to this fee according to
this theory
everything that we observe is
essentially an illusion
reality as we know it is made up of
fields and
disturbances in these fields so there is
a photon field there is a proton field
there is an electron field
and these fields permeate the entire
universe
it's the same field everywhere and these
particles protons neutrons electrons
etc are merely localized disturbances
in these fields and it is the
interaction of these
various disturbances in the fields and
the other
other fields and it is the interaction
that causes the forces that we
experience the force
the forces of electromagnetism the
strong nuclear force weak nuclear force
and so on
so the entire universe is essentially
comprised of
fields there are 17 fields in all that's
the standard model of physics
and there are four bosons so the
for the 17 particles are there are six
uh quarks there are six uh leptons
and you have four bosons and the bosons
are the carriers of the forces
so according to this theory all of these
bosons
should be massless but we find that
the w and z bosons the mediators of the
weak of the weak force actually have
mass and so to explain the fact that
these bosons have mass
a new particle had to be theorized it
was in the 1960s i believe that peter
higgs and a couple of other physicists
postulated hypothesized that there
exists one more boson
one more particle whose interaction with
the other particles
endows those particles with mass and
that is the higgs boson
so it is the interaction of all these
different fields and particles with the
higgs boson field
that imbues them with mass so certain
particles
interact more strongly with the higgs
field so they are more massive
certain particles interact less strongly
with this field so they are less massive
and particles such as the photon don't
interact with the field at all
that's why they are massless so that is
the higgs boson in the higgs field
and this particle was the last particle
of the standard model
to be discovered it was discovered in
the year 2012
in the large hadron collider and
physicists
particle physicists had been searching
for it for a very very long time
journalists called it the god particle
and particle physicists called it the
goddamn particle because it was so hard
to find
so it's been found finally a few years
ago and so that's what it is that's what
the higgs boson is and that's what the
higgs field
is it's what gives the universe and its
particles
mass so that's why we exist if there was
no mass
then we would not exist the universe
would be a very different place
so that is the higgs boson in the higgs
field
next question
so this is by akash puller what's your
opinion about the recent findings
hinting at the man-made origins of the
coronavirus
in a chinese lab and is this virus a bio
weapon
so for a very long time we have been
told
that this is a natural virus it evolved
naturally it came from bats supposedly
in the wet market in wuhan
but what we find is that bats are unable
to
be infected with this virus
so clearly it's not come from bats and
we have been told to follow the science
follow the science
but the fact is that the people who talk
the most about science
online are the ones who know the least
about science
and it's not about following the science
it's about following
who benefited from this pandemic this is
a geopolitical matter it's not a
scientific matter
if you create a virus in a lab and
release it in the world
you're going to make sure that you're
going to erase all traces of its origin
and therefore science will not be able
to find the source because you have
erased it
and therefore this is not a matter of
science it's a matter of
following the money who has benefited
the most from this pandemic
so the numbers are very clear if you
look at the numbers of the past year or
so
you will find that the entire world's
gdp has been shrinking
india's gdp has shrunk by about seven
percent or so the u.s gdp has shrunk the
uk gdp has shrunk
every major economy in the world has
seen a shrinkage of its gdp
or maybe a very small tiny growth of the
gdp
but nothing like it was supposed to be
now if we look at china's gdp i have
recently found that it has grown by 18
over the last year so over the past
decade or so china's gdp was growing at
less than 10
but suddenly it has seen the spurt of 18
percent
so how did china manage to
achieve such an enormous spurt of growth
while everybody else has seen a
shrinkage in the gdp
so clearly china has benefited from this
pandemic
and to a great extent they have been
able to place a lot of distance between
them and the rest of the competition
so i believe that this is a man-made
virus it was designed by china
and it was released strategically
for example in 2020 you had these
chinese tourists in italy
who are saying that i am chinese i'm not
a virus please hug me and
the poor italians would go and hug them
out of compassion
because they're afraid of being called
racist or whatever and that's how this
virus spread
and china had already banned travel
within china but they were allowing
people to travel
outside of china and if you look at
china's history over the past
10 20 years you will say that whenever
there is an
outbreak of a of a virus in africa for
example the ebola virus outbreak
in 20 in the early 2010s then the
chinese would send scientists
to these locations ostensibly to provide
aid for humanitarian purposes but what
they were actually doing was they were
collecting samples of these exotic
viruses
and these samples go back to china and
they are analyzed and they are tested
and i presume something else is also is
also done with these
samples of viruses so the chinese have
amassed
a great library of various viruses and
they have been testing them and doing
various
various things with these viruses so i
am not surprised that they have released
this virus this this the current
coronavirus is
thankfully not that virulent it's not
that deadly
if it was the ebola virus which would
have been released the
consequences would have been
catastrophic so i am pretty certain
that this is an engineered outbreak this
is a bio weapon
we all thought that 2020 was the year of
the virus i
am getting the feeling that the 2020s
are the decade of the virus
i hope i'm wrong but let's see but i am
pretty sure that this is
not a natural virus and and now the us
government is also
kind of publicly saying that there is
something more to this virus than a
natural origin
so the truth is coming out now for a
long time the western media did not
speak about this
they acted like agents of the chinese
they were concentrating on india they
were talking about how many cases are in
india
they were concentrating on the
cremations that are happening in india
and they were not questioning the
chinese who are not releasing any
numbers of how many
cases they have had and how many deaths
they've had the chinese have released no
numbers at all for the past year
and the western media has not deemed it
fit to question the chinese
and they are concentrating on india so
it's clear that even that the western
media
has been bought out by the chinese it's
very clear i don't think there's any
doubt at all
and even facebook was censoring posts
that
raised questions about the origins of
the virus so i'm glad it's coming out in
the open now
and i hope that the world takes
adequate measures to
preclude further occurrences of such
releases releases of of man-made viruses
so i i'm pretty convinced that this is a
man-made
bio-weapon next question
okay this is by piercing
have you seen the documentary the
phenomenon which talks about ufos and
extraterrestrial sightings
the u.s is also going to declassify some
info
what are my thoughts about ufos and
extraterrestrial sightings
and it being confirmed by many
individuals and
decorated government and military
officers across the world
so these um confirmations are mostly
from
u.s government sources and u.s military
sources
so you know like i said earlier i
am convinced that there is
extraterrestrial life
in our own solar system and outside i'm
convinced that there are intelligent
aliens as well in various star systems
around the world around the universe
but i am not sure that they have visited
us we still don't have enough
data you will see that there is no
scientist
who is making any comments about this no
scientist is commenting about this
and the reason is that we don't have
sufficient data to come to
any kind of uh proper conclusion about
the
about the origin of these
extraterrestrial sightings
so let me explain what i mean by this
let's say that the us government
declares that rainbows don't exist
then your your reaction is going to be
what nonsense
we know that rainbows exist we have all
seen rainbows they have been
documented to exist there are so many
photographs
and videos of rainbows worldwide so
there is documentary evidence
and a massive amount of documentary
evidence that rainbows exist
and i have seen one myself so you are
lying rainbows do exist
now what if the us government says that
comets don't exist
then again your reaction will be but we
know that comets exist we have seen
comets some of us have seen comments
comments
and astronomers have been describing
comets observing comets for centuries
and in the 20th century onwards we have
a massive amount of
photographic and video evidence of
comets taken by
thousands of astronomers and
non-astronomers worldwide
so there's a massive amount of evidence
irrefutable evidence that comets exist
now the us government is saying that
ufos
exist and here is our footage
and you will find that this is black and
white footage very grainy
it's hard to make out what it is and
they say that this
footage comes from us air force and u.s
navy cameras
so my question i have two questions
first of all why do the ufos
make themselves apparent why do these
ufos reveal themselves only to us
government and u.s military sources
why is that and secondly the u.s
military
has the world's greatest and latest
technology
so why are they releasing only grainy
black and white videos
i am sure that they have extremely high
definition video
capabilities in their military planes in
their aircraft
so why are only grainy black and white
images being released
what is the what is the reason for that
and why are these aliens showing
themselves only to the us government
why are there no ufo sightings
in mumbai why are there no ufo sightings
in berlin
in beijing in tokyo why is it always on
why is there no ufo scientific in
manhattan
where thousands of people can see it at
the same time and photograph it
and video and take videos why are there
no multiple
source sightings of ufos why it is why
is it always the us government
and the us military so that is what
makes me
extremely skeptical about these ufo
claims
so i you know what when i was a kid i
was fascinated with ufos
but as i grew up and i and i became a
scientist i realized that we do not have
sufficient evidence to make
a decision one way or the other whether
they exist or not
clearly there are unexplained aerial
phenomena that are
cited from time to time some of these
have been explained
some of them are still unexplained but
these
releases of videos by the us government
they look like plants to me
it's too creepy i feel that it's to
create a certain kind of narrative
which has a long term political or
geopolitical objective so i am extremely
extremely skeptical skeptical about the
current
rash of ufo disclosures that the us
government made
government is making i am not at all
convinced about these
claims right okay next question
what is the difference between an
astronomer and
an astrophysicist this is by aniket raj
so an astronomer is somebody who
observes
celestial events who observes the
planets and the stars
and the constellations and
records the data of these observations
so it is an observational
science and an observational art that's
what astronomy is
you don't need to be a physicist to be
an astronomer
it helps to understand physics but in
the past people have been doing
gastronomy for thousands of years
without
understanding the laws of physics
because thousands of years ago we did
not have the knowledge that we have
today
so astronomy is an observational art and
an observational science
astrophysics on the other hand is about
taking this observational evidence and
the observational data
and applying the laws of physics as we
know them
to this data to understand the nature of
the universe
to understand what drives things like
star formation than the deaths of stars
and the evolution of stars
what drives the formation and evolution
of galaxies and nebulae
and essentially what is the nature of
the universe
and all of that so it involves physics
it also involves some amount of
chemistry
and astrobiology involves the
understanding of biology as well
so that is the difference between an
astronomer and an astrophysicist an
astrophysicist is somebody who is
of a trained physicist and who applies
the laws of physics to understand
the universe better so that is the
fundamental difference one is one is an
observational science and art the other
one is about
analysis and and deduction
and observe and it you take the
observations and you analyze them
and you put forth theories and models
of various phenomena that you observe so
that is what
astrophysicists do
next question
this is by akshat chobay what is my
opinion about the one china policy
and should india continue to accept it
yeah that's a good question so the
chinese say that china
is one entity one nation and
nobody should question it and everybody
should agree
to the chinese perception of what their
geographical
boundaries are so china has
invaded and occupied and annexed tibet
we should accept it they are now
claiming the south china sea
we should accept it in the future god
forbid
they should they would they want to they
want to invade and capture
arunachal pradesh and they would like
the world
to accept except it is part of china
so there is a concept called reciprocity
in international relations
i will honor your wishes if you honor
mine
and india also should have a one india
policy
which which includes the entirety of
jammu and kashmir
including exciting it should include the
whole of arunachal pradesh which is
already under our jurisdiction and it
will remain
under our jurisdiction and we would like
china
to adhere and respect adhere to
and respect our
our geographical boundaries and they
refuse to do that
they do not want to respect our
geographical
claims but they want us to accept
their geographical claims and their
geographical claims are always expanding
they have territorial disputes with
almost all of their neighbors
japan japan and
russia as well the russian dispute is
right now
under the carpet it will soon pop up
again it pops up from time to time in
the chinese media
and with every other with almost every
other uh
nation that has a common border with
china so they have this expansionist
hegemonic tendency and they want to keep
expanding their territories and they
want us to
accept that one china policy so my
stand is very simple we should accept
their one china policy if they accept
the one india policy and they if they
accept the geographical boundaries of
india
as we have always known them to be
essentially china has no business being
in tibet
or at the border of india see china has
existed as a separate civilization as an
independent
civilization for the past two and a half
or three thousand years
and india has been around for ten
thousand years or more and india and
china have never had a common boundary
until the past say 60 or 70 years so
this
border tension is a very new thing
and it is something that the chinese
communist party has created out of thin
air india and china have historically
never had
any sort of conflict ever so the chinese
communist party has created this
conflict by capturing tibet and then
laying claims on indian territory so if
the chinese want india
to accept their one china policy they
should first
quickly agree to a proper border
demarcation
and they should accept our historical
long-standing millennia old
geographical boundaries and then we can
think of
accepting their so-called one china
policy
so that is what i believe the world
needs to
stand up against china and stand
together against china china is
china's rise is not at all peaceful
china doesn't believe in a peaceful rise
it believes in
continuous and perpetual expansion
whether it's the expansion of its
borders the expansion of its economy
mercantilism expanding into other poor
countries and
and and laying debt traps upon them like
they've done sri lanka and many african
countries
so it's an expansionist hegemonic power
and it does not wish the world
well so it may not be resorting to
military violence at this stage
but it is clearly not a not a nation
that wishes well upon the world
so i would say that the world should
stand up against china and this one
china policy should be accepted only if
china
seizes these expansionist and hegemonic
ambitions of its of office and if it
behaves
according to the so-called accepted
international laws
right next question
so this is by aditya can ai take over
the world
if yes what are the chances of ai taking
over humanity
and b can we the humans fight artificial
intelligence
and win right so
this has been in the news for quite some
time now artificial intelligence because
we are making
great strides in the progress of this
technology
we have things like machine learning
self-learning algorithms
neural networks that are growing and
learning on their own and so on so forth
so the question is
can ai take over the world
for ai to take over the world it would
first need to become
self-aware it would need to become aware
of the external world
it would need to become conscious and it
would need to
start to understand the difference
between itself
and the external world so think about
when a human being is born they have no
awareness
of either themselves or the external
world it takes
several months for them to become aware
of their existence
as being separate from the existence of
the world and it takes time for them
many years to understand the world
properly
to gather information to process that
information
to start seeing the patterns that recur
throughout the world
and to make sense of the world overall
so it takes many years for a human being
to
achieve that level of understanding of
the world at which
they can start making a difference in
the world now ais would also
need to go through these steps if they
become conscious and self-aware
and for them to take over the world they
would need to be
able to harness unlimited energy they
would be able to
they would need to be able to harness
unlimited energy and resources
and be in charge of decision-making
processes
the world over only then would they be
able to take over the world
so i think it's it's going to be a very
long time before that happens
before ais have access to that level of
resources
and they have that level of
understanding of the world
i think it's not going to happen in the
next decade at least that ai's will
become self-aware
maybe in the next 20 years definitely i
would say in the next 50 years ais would
become self-aware conscious
so to say we don't really know what
consciousness is but
it's possible and my real fear
is that it's not the pro the big problem
is not that ais will become self-aware
it's that ais will give certain people
certain institutions certain
organizations and certain countries
almost unlimited power so that is the
immediate threat of ai
because of these capabilities
private corporations have started
transcending national boundaries
they have started impugning upon
national sovereignty the worldwide
it's already happening so this is all
because of
the power of computing and the power of
algorithms so that's already happening
that is the immediate threat
ai is becoming conscious is a threat
that is in the future
and uh so the chances do exist
but these chances are not immediate
maybe in the next 20 to 50 years ais
may be able to pose a genuine threat to
human beings
if ais actually take over the world
then i think that the chance of human
beings fighting them back
and winning is next to zero so the main
thing is we should never
allow an artificial intelligence to
have access to unlimited resources and
to have access to decision making
processes it should not have decision
making abilities to
make changes in the world and it should
not have access to unlimited resources
and unlimited power it should be
self-contained
and it should be limited in scope then
only can we keep it under control if it
actually becomes
conscious and self-aware and intelligent
so that's the answer that's my
perspective
next question
okay this is by shubham pandey do you
believe that vikings
actually existed and yes and if yes
how did such strong men vanish vanish
and is vinland a true place so yes of
course the vikings did
exist and they have not vanished their
descendants
are very much alive
uh the scandinavian nations these are
the nations that
are home to the descendants of these
vikings so that's
norway denmark sweden to some extent
finland
greenland uh iceland
and also the united kingdom the british
isles because there were lots of
viking invasions in the british isles
about a thousand years before today
and also france because the normans the
french normans
were the descendants of these vikings so
yes
they did exist and they have not
vanished their descendants are
very much present in the world they are
present in northern europe and western
europe
is wind land a true place yes so wind
land is
most likely uh the northern
tip of newfoundland which is uh
an island in northwestern
north america it's part of canada today
so they have found
evidence of viking of one viking
settlement over there
it's called loss of so that is
clear irrefutable evidence that there
was a viking presence in north america
they have found one site thus far i'm
sure there are more
archaeological sites waiting to be
discovered
so it is definitely true that the
vikings crossed the atlantic ocean
much before christopher columbus they
discovered north america they even
settled there
we don't know what happened to the
descendants whether they interbred with
the
native americans and assimilated into
the population
or whether some sort of misfortune
befell them and then they vanished
we don't really know what happened but
yes they did cross over
and they did settle north america for
some time at least
okay next question
this is by mohit pal can you explain
how quantum is connected in our
day-to-day life
right so how what is the relevance of
quantum physics
and the quantum world in our day-to-day
life
so you see the world that we live in it
emerges
out of the microscopic world the flesh
and blood that we have in our bodies the
fabric we wear
the world around us it is made up of
microscopic
particles and all of these particles
these microscopic
particles the atomic and molecular and
sub-atomic level
obey the laws of quantum mechanics
quantum physics and quantum field theory
so everything every phenomenon that we
observe
in the mundane day-to-day
world is a phenomenon that emerges from
the quantum
level now certain quantum phenomena
are present to us are observable
to the naked eye for example if you see
a crystal a crystal of quartz for
example
the crystal structure the crystalline
structure of quartz or
any other crystal is governed by the
laws of quantum mechanics
so that is a quantum it's a macroscopic
quantum object
that we can perceive in our daily life
if you look outside the window
in the morning and look at the sun i
mean don't look directly at it but you
see the sunlight
that sunlight comes from the sun the sun
is an
enormous nuclear reaction
it's an enormous fusion reaction
which is a quantum process and a fun
fact
every photon of sunlight that emerges
out of the sun
takes thousands of years to emerge out
of the sun
maybe millions of years because it is
absorbed and reabsorbed and emitted and
reabsorbed
trillions of times inside the sun before
it's able to emerge out
of the sun's uh atmosphere so
every photon of sunlight that reaches us
was born
either thousands or millions of years
ago inside the sun in the interior of
the sun
and it takes that much time to traverse
the distance from the interior of the
sun to
outside of it so that's a quantum
phenomenon
and everything else that we observe
emerges out of the quantum domain
the laws of quantum physics are not
observable to us to the most part
because
quantum phenomena either collapse or
they decohere
and they become classical phenomena
which is the laws of classical physics
so that is the relationship between the
quantum world and
the ordinary world the ordinary world
emerges out of the quantum world and
it it the laws of quantum physics are
very
non-intuitive they are very strange and
the paradox is that they give rise
to the laws of physics that we know and
the which seems so
ordinary to us except the law of gravity
which we still don't understand
so that is how the ordinary world
emerges out of the quantum world that is
the relationship there is a
direct relationship between the quantum
world and our day-to-day world
next question
so this is by i don't know and
it says why is the indian education
system based on ranks
why is the syllabus outdated i am 17 a
non-science student
i regret why the system is all about
marks and ranks is there any way left
will i be able to create tech products
through self-study
what advice would you give to me so i
would say that yes india's education
system
is obsolete it is outdated
it still behaves as if we are living in
the 19th century it's based upon
marks and ranks and degrees so the
objective of the system was to create
clerks
if you have a degree in the education in
the indian education system
it means that you
you are obedient you don't ask questions
you can write clearly you can write long
essays and you will make a good clerk
that's essentially all the indian
education system does
it is designed to turn out clerks and
peons
it is not designed to turn out leaders
or thought leaders
or innovators it crushes your creativity
and your intellect and replaces it with
with something very very different and
something that is not conducive to
having
a good society and a strong society and
a strong nation
so i would say that if you are you
should not give up hope because
the coming years are going to see the
emergence of
technologies and technology is already
permeating the entire world
today you don't need to have a job in
india you can have a job anywhere in the
world from
while sitting at home so if it's all
about skills
you need to learn skills if you can if
you can you know how to do programming
if you know how to create websites then
you can create a bunch of websites
create a portfolio advertise it online
and you can get work
very well paying work if you know how to
do video editing
you will get you will get work as a
video editor if you know graphic design
if you know audio design audio editing
or any of these skills if you don't
search engine optimization so these are
all skills that don't
require any degree you can
excel at these things without ever
needing to earn a degree
and when somebody is looking for a
programmer they don't look at their
degree they look at the kind of work
they've done
so what you need to do is you need to
acquire these
skills and you can acquire skills like
coding like programming
website designing graphic designing you
can acquire all these skills
online by looking at youtube tutorials
and other websites
and all of this information is available
online for free
you just need to look for it so you can
acquire all of these skills
on your own without anybody's help and
once you have these skills you need to
showcase them in a portfolio
and that will give you the opportunity
to earn a great living online
from clients throughout the world
without ever needing a degree
so that so that's what the future holds
for us
it's a very good thing so it's it's
increasingly making the indian education
system obsolete
it's also making the global education
systems obsolete
so it's it's a very good period of time
actually for for people who
are skilled so it's going to make all
the degrees obsolete but
right now this coming decade at least
degrees will still be relevant in india
but they will increasingly fade out of
demand
so i would say that you need to acquire
these skills whatever you are good at
whatever you
you feel that you will be good at
acquire these skills practice create a
portfolio
advertise the portfolio and and you will
do well
you will you will find lots of work
online so that's what the future holds
so you should not feel lost you should
not feel
hopeless there's a lot of hope be
positive
and work on it
all right next question
this is from
uh the question is regarding the origins
of our civilization
gotham buddha's history is quite well
recorded
yet a buddha does not drop out of thin
air without having a huge preceding
history of a highly evolved civilization
when do you think our civilization must
have developed stable advanced
societies so palace you are absolutely
right
uh somebody like the buddha does not
drop out of thin air there has to be a
long historical precedent
and a great deal of socio-cultural and
civilizational context
somebody like the buddha cannot evolve
out of a barbaric primitive
society somebody like the buddha or even
mahavira
cannot emerge out of society which is
not highly evolved
so it's clear that the the buddha and
mahavira of jainism who are believed to
be contemporaries
it is clear that these two great souls
these two great individuals
were the outcome of a very ancient
civilization of a civilization that was
already very ancient
two and a half thousand years before
today
and we know that the buddha is not the
first buddha there is
according to buddhist tradition there
were many buddhas before the last one
before siddharth gotham and even in the
jain tradition
mahavir is just one of a long line of
great
jain tirthankars so it's very clear that
indian
historical tradition it has
says that india had a very very long
history before
the buddha and before mahavira and
the greek historical sources corroborate
this because
greek ambassadors who came to the court
of
our emperor chandragupta maurya they
wrote that the indian calendrical system
of that time dated back to at least 6
600 and something bce
so that is a whole lot of time that's
almost 9 000 years before today
and there were records and of lineages
and dynasties that stretched
all the way back to before 6000 bce
so that tells you that we have been our
our ancestors were recording
events in our indigenous calendar
they had been doing this for at least 8
000 years before today
so it's clear that a culture that
develops a calendar
would have been highly evolved even
before that
so that would tell you that indian
culture had been evolving
for thousands of years before 6000 bce
and that's how they were able to mature
and create a highly accurate calendar
so i would say that this is evidence
that india's civilization is millennia
millennia older
than gautam buddha and mahavira it goes
back to
at least six thousand seven thousand bce
most likely it is much older than even
ten thousand years before today
so we have sufficient evidence from
multiple sources from archaeological
sources
calendrical sources from greek sources
etc
that all point in the same direction
that india's civilization is extremely
ancient
it may well date back to before 10 000
bce
before 10 000 years before today so
i hope that historical research
proceeds in the direction there is a lot
to uncover we are at the very beginning
of i believe a new phase of historical
research with
india as the focus so it's a very
exciting time ahead and i look forward
to that
next question
this is by sarthak van kerev what if two
black holes of equal mass
merged so
if two black holes of equal mass were to
merge
let's say both black holes have a mass
of 30 solar masses each so each black
hole
has 30 solar masses and they were to
merge in an in spiral event
then what would happen is that they
would merge and there would be
a single black hole that would emerge
out of this merger and the mass
of this new black hole would be less
than the total
less than the sum of these two masses so
if you have two black holes of 30 solar
masses each
they would expect them to create a black
hole of 60 solar masses
but what actually happens is that the
new black hole will have
three or four solar masses less so the
new black hole would have
56 or 57 solar masses approximately
so the question is where did this mass
go where what what accounts for this
missing mass
and the answer to that is that that
missing mass was converted into
gravitational energy
when an inspiral event happens and
a merger of two large black holes
happens
there it it this this merger gives forth
an enormous burst of gravitational waves
it's like
an enormous tsunami of gravitational
waves
and this tsunami of gravitational waves
carries away a lot of energy
so it takes away a lot of the energy of
these two
black holes the merging black holes and
we all know einstein's equation the
most famous equation of the in the world
e equals m c squared
so according to this equation energy and
mass are equivalent
so this energy that was taken away in
the form of gravitational radiation
is subtracted from the from the mass
of the resultant black hole so that's
why the resultant black hole has a mass
that is less than the sum total
of the masses of the two original parent
black holes
so that's what happens when two black
holes of equal mass
merge and this is something that's been
observed actually
uh when the first uh detection was made
of a black hole merger it was found that
the two black holes had uh
masses that the resultant black hole had
a mass that was less than the
mass of the two than the total of the
mass of the two original black holes you
can look it up online
right next question
this is by lusna pradhan details about
ma saraswati river so
the saraswati river has been an object
of great controversy for
more than a century
the first western records of this river
were
date back to the 19th century i believe
or even before that when
british archaeologists and explorers
found evidence of a dry riverbed in
western india
and they interviewed many local people
and who all told them this ancient story
that there was once a great river over
here which was named the saraswati and
it is
it has dried out a long time ago but we
still
believe that it is flowing underground
or something like that
so these records have been there they
have they date back to the 19th century
at least and these are european records
and there is clear evidence of a great
dry riverbed if you look at google earth
so if you know where to look you will
find that there is a great dry riverbed
which is
enormous it's an enormous ancient river
which has dried up
and so this has been an object of great
controversy
western historians and even indian
historians have been denying this
for almost a century they have been
denying the the existence of such a
river
they have been calling it a myth but
unfortunately for them now the
scientific evidence is is too much
to ignore there is incontrovertible
evidence of the presence of a
great ancient river in western india
it flowed from the himalayas all the way
to the so-called arabian sea
it flowed into the arabian sea uh in the
region of
present-day kach so this is a very great
river it was greater than all of the
other rivers in the sindhu region it was
definitely
bigger and wider than the indus river
and therefore this ancient phase of our
civilization that is called the harappan
phase
of india civilization should actually be
called the saraswati phase
of india's civilization because this dry
riverbed is exactly where our history is
our etihas says it would be so it is
clearly no
none other than the great ancient
service of the river and it has been
determined to have dried out about
1500 bce or thereabouts
and what we find is that there are
thousands of unexplored archaeological
sites
on the banks of this dry riverbed and
there are more ancient archaeological
sites on the banks of the saraswati
than on the banks of the indus so
clearly this was a more significant
river
than the ancient in this indus river
and what happened was that this river
dried out because of climate change
so this so what happened was that in
ancient times the indian monsoon was
much more intense
it was much heavier than what it is
today
and around 6000 bce or thereabouts the
indian monsoon started declining slowly
and the saraswati river was fed by the
monsoons and also by glacial melt from
the himalayas
so because of the because of the decline
the gradual decline of the indian
monsoon the river started
started drying up over the centuries in
the millennia
and it stopped reaching the sea about
1500 years
bce and even today some portion of it is
still
extent in the northern part of india
it's called the
river it is a seasonal river it is dry
for some months and it is
it is it flows with some water for some
months in the year
so there is no doubt about the evidence
of this river
and the everyday the
the fact that this river existed is it
it gives us a very good
handle on the date of the rig veda
because according to mainstream history
so called mainstream mystery
the rigveda was written around 1200 bce
now the fact is that the rigveda
extensively mentions the saraswati river
and it mentions a great river it calls
it
the mother of floods it caused the
saraswati
a loudly roaring river and a river that
was
prone to flooding very often it was a
clearly a great river it was clearly a
much greater river than the indus
and that is what the rigveda has
recorded so clearly
the rigveda was written at a time when
the river saraswati was in its prime
and not when it was drying out or after
it dried out
so that would place the rigveda to
around 6000 bce
8 000 years before today and not at 1200
bce
like our so-called eminent historians
would like us to be
to believe so things are changing
scientific evidence is
dismantling and debunking the colonial
narratives of history that we have been
learning and we are still learning
today so it's great so so the saraswati
river did exist
and it is now being written about and it
is being uh
papers scientific research papers have
been published about it in
very prestigious journals like nature so
it's now become mainstream
it is now accepted that it existed and
it's extremely inconvenient for
colonial theories like the rn invasion
theory and so forth
so that's a brief it's a brief uh
piece of information about this river
next question
it is by sumona day can you please speak
about
the origin of the bengalis are they
of aryan or dravidian origin
okay so bengal
so bengal has had a very long history
like the rest of india
uh before the
islamic invasion of bengal it was called
vanga
vangadesh so the word vanga became banga
and it
became known as bengal eventually so
before
the islamization of large parts of
bengal it was called vangadesh or vanga
pradesh
and the british when they first reached
bengal
they wrote about it as being the most
prosperous
province of india so it was
an extremely prosperous beautiful
bountiful land
full of extremely civilized people
and very prosperous people there was a
great deal of prosperity very high
living standards
and that's how it was and the history of
bengal
goes back at least 2000 years
there are these archaeological there's
this archaeological site called chandra
ketugar
in bengal which is more than 2000 years
old and it has this beautiful
carvings and sculptures of all kinds of
social events kings and queens and
tournaments and festivals and
celebrations and temples
so it is a very interesting
representation of
the life of of ordinary people and other
people as well
in ancient bengal so this evidence is at
least
2000 years old it goes back to around
2300 2400 bce
but as with the rest of india there has
been almost no
archaeological work done in bengal
if you were to do that i would i am sure
that the
history of bengal would be extended to
many thousand years before
before today so like the rest of india
bengal has had a very
long and prosperous history it's only in
the past 300 years or so that bengal was
ravaged by colonialism it was
subjected to repeated famines
terrible terrible famines by the british
millions of people died each time
and it was reduced to poverty and
the partition bengal in the early 20th
century
this eventually led to the formation of
bangladesh
so so so that's a bit about the origin
of bengal and the bengali people
now to the question of whether they are
aryan or dravidian the bengalis are
neither aryan nor dravidian they are
indians
there is no such thing as aryans and
dravidians
this is a colonial construction you will
see no reference to the to dravidians
before because before the british came
into india
you will see no reference to to
dravidian people or dravidian lands
or davidian kingdoms in ancient indian
literature
none of it at all it is a british
construction they have tried to link it
to some ancient text
by twisting some pronunciations of some
words
but this is a colonial construction it
was designed
to divide india and to alienate the
north and the south from each other
that is why this aryan dravidian divide
was constructed
and here's what the iron dravidian
divide says
it says that the people of northern and
western india are the descendants of
aryan invaders
and the people of southern india are the
descendants of dravidians who are the
original inhabitants of india
so it says that these are two different
races these are two different
ethnicities it says that these are
different genetics
this is what the aryan and dravidian
theory
says that these are two different ethnic
groups
different races now let me debunk this
once
and for all let me okay let me open a
webpage and show it to you
just give me a minute please i'm going
to
show this
all right here it is so this
is this is a
a news item which says that there is
this little girl
who was born in florida she was two
years old in 2018 or 2019
and she had leukemia she has leukemia
and she needs
a rare blood group a very very rare
blood type
which is found only let me show you
uh one second
okay this is the one so this is a
two-year-old florida girl
who is of most likely indian origin
and she needs a very very kind of rare
kind of blood
and only people of pakistani indian or
iranian descent
are carriers of this compatible blood
group
and out of those only four percent
people so it says that
people of indian
pakistani and india and iranian origin
have this blood group and nobody else in
the world has it
so what does this tell you it tells you
that the people of india
iran and pakistan are the same ethnicity
they are the same race and when they say
india it means the indian subcontinent
india pakistan afghanistan nepal
sri lanka maldives etc
so this is proof that the people of the
indian subcontinent
and the people of iran they are one
single ethnicity because this blood type
or blood antigen is found only in this
particular
segment of the world's population it's
not found among africans it's not found
in eastern asian people it's not found
in europe it's not found
in the americas or australia or anywhere
else
only in indian subcontinent and in iran
so this and it does not say that only
north indians
are applicable or eligible or it does
not say that the south indians are not
eligible
it means that the people of northern
india and iran
who are supposedly aryans share this
with the people of southern india who
are supposedly dravidians
right so this completely debunks
this notion that
the people of southern india and the
people of northern india are two
different ethnicities in two different
races
if they share this particular antigen
which is not found anywhere else in the
world it conclusively proves that they
are one single race and one single
ethnicity
it means there is no aryan dravidian
divide we may look different
on the outside some of us may be taller
some of us may be shorter
some of us may have fair skin some of us
may have darker skin
and yet we are the same ethnicity mataya
muralidharan is the same ethnicity as
imran khan
right that's what it means we are the
same people
so there is no such thing as aryan or
dravidian the people of bengal
are indians they are neither aryan nor
dravidian they are simply indians
and there is answer to your question
okay
next question
right this is from sanchita mandal
i am a mother of an eight-year-old girl
in this covid situation
schooling system is broken down can you
please guide me how
in future education system will be and
how can we
how can small students prepare for the
future
so i kind of answered this earlier but
let me go back into that
small students students young students
like people who are like kids who are
eight years old and thereabouts
they have a very bright future ahead of
them because the future of the world
is going to is going to be all about
technology it's going to be all about
skills degrees will very soon become
irrelevant
if you have skills like programming like
website design
like uh graphic design video editing
search
engine optimization and much more skills
such as these technological skills
then you will be able to prosper in the
future world in the coming world
of the coming years so i would say that
a child who is eight years old should
have plan a and plan b
and both should be executed
simultaneously plan a
is go through the indian education
system get your degrees
go get your 10 standard degree 1200
degree get a college degree
but also at the same time focus
on developing skills technological
skills
all kids are great at technology
especially indian kids indian kids are
the most intelligent kids
in the entire world they learn
technology
very naturally right you will find the
six month old kids who are you know
fiddling around on smartphones so
i would say that go through the
educational system
get your eight-year-old girl the degrees
that are required
but also make sure that she gets a good
uh
good amount of education in developing
technological skills because in the
future
that's what's going to be really
relevant
so that's that's my short answer the
the future is is going to be great we
have to stay positive we
we should be positive and we should
prepare for it properly so
this is how we do that all right next
question
this is from anshu gupta please explain
the law of karma
so in physics there are these uh
conservation laws the law of
conservation of momentum the law of
conservation of mass the law of
conservation of charge
and so on so
now karma is not about physics it's not
about science it is something that
transcends science karma is about
philosophy and spirituality
but the law of karma is also a
conservation law
it is the law of conservations of
actions
and their merits and demerits across
lifetimes
it says that the law of karma says that
everybody has
an immortal soul and that whatever
actions you take you perform in a
certain lifetime
will accrue merits and demerits based on
the nature of those actions if you do
good things you will accrue
merit if you do evil things you will
accrue demerits
and all of these merits and demerits
will be conserved across
lifetimes as long as the soul exists in
as long as the universe exists
so that is the law of karma put very
simply
it's the law of conservation of the
merits and demerits of actions
applicable to every soul across
lifetimes
that's how a physicist like me would see
it
hope that helps all right next question
okay this is by vanch bora how did
scientists figure out about the
multiverse
and is there any proof about it
so uh the multiverse theory has
numerous origins one of the theories
comes out of string theory
uh the so-called spring theory landscape
which which which
hypothesizes that there are then at
least there are at least 10 to the 500
different
configurations of universes and maybe
much more than that
so that's what string theory says uh
quantum mechanics
has an interpretation called the many
worlds interpretation
its originator was hugh everett who was
ridiculed for it
and now it is one of the most widely
accepted
explanations or interpretations of
quantum mechanics so according to the
many worlds theory of in quantum
mechanics
every time you have you make an
observation it splits the universe into
two branches
so every time you observe something or
you make a choice
the universe splits into two branches
and
and both uh outcomes exist
simultaneously
but your consciousness exists only in
one of the branches
of the universe but the other branch of
the universe has a copy of you with a
separate consciousness
who has made a different choice so for
example you flip a coin
and you see that it's heads but what
happens when you flip a coil is that the
universe splits off into two branches
and in the other branch of the universe
there is a copy of you who has got the
result as tails
so that's the simplest form
of explaining the many worlds
interpretation of quantum mechanics
there are other interpretations as well
for example if you were living in a
simulation the simulation hypothesis
then a supercomputer or a hyper computer
that could create a simulation
that we live in could create possibly
multiple such simulations
which could be looked upon as a
multiverse
so there are many origins there are many
possible configurations of this
multiverse hypothesis
but it is simply a hypothesis it is not
a theory
so a hypothesis is an educated guess
it is a possible explanation of
something
but a hypothesis needs to be supported
by
by experimental and observational
evidence for it to become an accepted
theory
so the multiverse is merely a hypothesis
because we cannot test whether there are
multiple universes
we cannot even leave our own planet we
cannot even leave our solar system so
how will we leave our universe
and test whether there are whether there
are other universes out there
so as of now there is no way to test
the multiverse hypothesis that's why it
is merely
a hypothesis and not a theory
so that's what is it's all about so
there is no proof
it doesn't have any proof thus far it's
just
a hypothesis it as of now it belongs in
the realm of philosophy
not of science okay one more question
and then i will take some live questions
so this is by ritwik what do you think
about
india's foreign policy about china india
has repeated the same mistakes over and
over
indian politicians and bureaucrats have
never taken china seriously lacked the
vision to understand china
why are we so confused
do you think bureaucrats are bought by
china
do you think we need young leadership in
the 30s and 40s
do you think our system is too old
people centric rather than youth centric
i think that i agree with you
i think that our system is too old
people-centric
it needs to be more youth-centric i'm
not i'm not saying that we should get
rid of the old people
absolutely not old people have a great
deal of experience and wisdom
what we need is we need to have a
spectrum of age groups
we need to have a good amount of
representation of
younger people because it is the younger
people who have the dynamism and the
energy
and the new ideas and the understanding
of the new world that the old people
lack and what old people can contribute
is a deeper understanding of the past
and a great deal of experience
so what we need in our establishment in
our foreign policy establishment
and all our institutions is a judicious
harmonious blend of elderly people of
older people
and younger people and the emphasis
should always be on the future which
means younger people
so i would say that yes our system is
too old people-centric it's too
conservative and you are right our
system does not understand china
thus far all our so-called
foreign policy experts and strategic
experts have been experts about pakistan
in the past india's foreign policy was
all about pakistan pakistan pakistan
that's all you understood
that's all the media understood that's
all these experts understood
now after last year's events the galwan
clash and all that
they have suddenly morphed into china
experts
the fact is that they don't understand
china none of them
knows how to read or write mandarin
if you don't know how to read and write
mandarin you cannot read
chinese texts and everything that is
written about the chinese
strategic thought thought processes and
their
geopolitical outlook and world view
all of that is written in chinese
mandarin
so if you want to understand what the
chinese are thinking what they're
planning you
need to have a good understanding of the
mandarin language
and our experts the majority of our
experts lack that understanding they
don't understand
that language and they don't understand
china i'm not claiming to be a china
expert
i don't know mandarin so i am not an
expert in neither
are these people and i would say that
our foreign policy establishment has
this great
glaring drawback first of all it's too
small we have less than 2000 diplomats
to take on the entire world that is less
than the diplomatic strength of
singapore or japan
so for a country like india which
supposedly aspires to great power status
you need a much
greater foreign policy establishment
we need a greater core of diplomats
and they should be drawn for from
various disciplines not just from the
indian bureaucratic services so i agree
with you that there's a great deal of
reform that is needed
and that reform needs to happen very
quickly because as of now we do not
understand china
at all right so i think
uh i've taken about 20 questions let me
take a few live questions and then we
will wrap up
so i'll just take a look at uh the
comments
uh there's a question about the cold war
why does our educational
system already let me find that
wow there's a lot of questions thank you
everybody for all questions
uh
in the srinivas ramanujan
higgs boson i spoke about that uh
yes yes yes uh
yes balu i have i have spoken about the
higgs boson so
i'll take a different question
okay let's take this one please explain
quantum entanglement theory in layman's
language
so quantum entanglement theory is that
is a theory that two particles
are intrinsically entangled are
intrinsically
linked together and the and they remain
linked together
no matter where they are in the universe
so think about it like this in layman's
language let's say you have a pair
of shoes so you have a left shoe
and a right shoe now you pack these
separately
you send one shoe to your friend in
moscow
and you send the other shoe to your
friend in chennai
now let's say the shoe reaches chennai
before it reaches moscow
and your friend in chennai received the
package and he or she
opens the package and finds that it is
the right shoe
so what does it tell you about the
person who's in moscow what are they
gonna find
they're gonna find a left shoe in their
package
so the moment you open the contents of
one package
you immediately know the contents of the
other package
now instead of moscow let's say i spent
i sent that that package
to the andromeda galaxy let's say i was
able to send it within the next one hour
hypothetically and then if i open the
package over here
in chennai then i will know immediately
that the package in andromeda
has what configuration of shoe so this
information seems to travel faster than
the speed of light
and this is just a layman's picture of
how it is but particles are entangled
and the problem is that until we observe
a particle
we have no way of knowing what state it
is in because if a particle has
stayed up in space straight down then
before you observe it it is in both
states at the same time
it's in a superposition of two states so
both entangled particles are in
superpositions
neither of these particles knows what
the other particle state is
and yet once you observe the state of
one particle
even if the other particle is 100 light
years away you will immediately know the
state of that particle as well
so the information seems to travel at
least
10 000 times faster than the speed of
light
and we know that there is a that this is
a true effect it's not
einstein was of the of the uh opinion
that this spooky action at a distance is
just an illusion there is a deeper lord
which which restores the causal
structure of the universe but that is
not the case
we have now realized that it is truly
spooky action at a distance
and we don't understand how it happens
the only plausible explanation
that we have of entanglement as of now
is what is known as
super determinism and there is a theory
that everything has been determined from
the very beginning
so every particle knows what's going to
happen
so it's like saying that everything is
written in the fate you know
so that is what super determinism
essentially is
it is that every future outcome of the
ut of the universe has been determined
in advance so that is one explanation of
quantum entanglement
so it is one of the mysteries of quantum
mechanics one of the one of the many
mysteries
right let me take another question
okay why do we dream
well dreaming is related to the mystery
of consciousness
we don't know how the brain works we
don't know how the mind works
we don't know what consciousness is and
yet when we sleep
when we are supposedly unconscious we
have these
dreams so it is and
once again sleep itself is a great
mystery we don't know why we sleep
and one of the strange things is that
when you have these neural networks
that mimic the structure of the brain
then you find that
even the neural networks need a period
of rest
otherwise they start outputting garbage
information
so if a neural network has been running
for let's say 12
12 to 14 hours you will find that it
needs
to undergo a period of rest otherwise
the
results that it is outputting become
garbage
so even neural networks need what seems
to be sleep
and do that dream as well we don't know
so this is one of the great
mysteries that science is currently
grappling with
there is so much that we don't know so
that's what it is right
so it's part of the mystery of
consciousness why do we dream as of now
we do not know
there are a number of theories maybe the
brain is processing the information it
has acquired during the daytime
maybe it is rearranging memories and
that manifests as dreams because of the
connections of the neurons and the
connections of various memories together
so these are all speculations these are
theories we do not have any
proof as of now about these
about about why this actually happens
okay let me take one more question
okay this is by anik my thoughts on
terraforming mars how much progress has
been made on this front
my thoughts on setting up a base on the
moon tapping asteroids as a source of
energy
well to terraform mars we would first
need to get to mars
and that is not going to happen anytime
immediately
maybe by the 2030s we may send the first
missions to mars there is the
americans will do it elon musk has plans
nasa has plans so the americans will
most likely
try doing this in the 2030s the russians
may have plans they may be working
with the chinese in this matter so
the first tentative baby steps will be
taken
most likely in the 2030s about reaching
mars
now in order to terraform a planet like
you would need a substantial human
presence on mars you would need
tens of thousands of people and you
would need to transfer a great deal of
equipment
to mars either transfer transfer it
there or to build
new equipment on mars using the local
resources so you would need to do mining
mining on mars you would need to extract
metals and other resources
create machines and create settlements
and then you can think about
terraforming the planet now
terraforming mars would basically what
what's what we are thinking is that we
should escape the earth and go to mars
because we have ruined earth we have
messed it up very badly
my my my point is that if we have messed
up the earth so badly
what is the i mean what is the
possibility that will not do the same on
mars
we're gonna have the same patterns of
behavior that we have here on earth
so what we'll do is we will mess up the
earth then we will escape to mars then
we will mess up mars as well
and then where do we go so that is the
dilemma that we are currently grappling
with because
the system that we are currently uh
following the system of this this
relentless pursuit of
endless growth of endless gdp growth
we think that we can have endless gdp
growth on a limited planet
on a planet with limited resources it is
only going to end up
in disaster so this system
this capitalist exploitative system
which exploits the environment
needs to be abandoned for something that
is better i am
not advocating marxism or socialism or
communism
i am just saying that we need a better
system than what what we are currently
following
so that's what we need to do
terraforming mars it may be possible
in the future i would not want us to
nuke mars
we have ice caps on the poles of mars
elon musk says we should nuke them to
quickly
bring about a radical change in the
in the atmosphere of mars i would
be strongly against that we should not
take actions that we have no way of
reversing
so as of now very little progress has
been made about this
my thoughts on setting up a base on the
moon it's going to happen very soon it's
going to happen in this decade
the first steps will be taken by the
americans most likely in 2024
the chinese are already making progress
they are sending
probes to the moon india has been trying
it
uh our last mission was a partial
success
chandrayaan-2 our lander could not make
it in one piece
we're going to try it again maybe this
year or the next year
so the americans are gonna are going to
have a base on the moon
by 24 25 definitely in this decade most
likely the chinese and the russians too
and i hope that the indian
government also takes steps because we
cannot afford to be left behind
in the space race what's going to happen
is that in the 21st century the nations
the two or three nations
that are going to be at the forefront of
space exploration
are going to be the two or three nations
that are going to lead the world
that's it's as simple as that so if
india has
any aspiration or any ambition of being
a global power and to have
a sovereign identity of its own then it
needs to strongly focus on space
exploration because the
technological spin-offs that come out of
space exploration
are extremely useful in geopolitical
applications
so that's what needs to happen
tapping asteroids is a source of energy
well asteroids will be mined for
metals most likely many asteroids
are metallic in nature iron asteroids
nickel also is found and various other
metals as well
so asteroid mining will happen
eventually in the next coming decades
definitely in the 21st century if we
don't mess things up
so it will the asteroid belt will be
tapped for metals and other resources
not necessarily for energy energy
will come from the moon because the the
lunar dust contains great amounts of
a rare isotope of helium which is not
found on earth
and that will be the fuel for future
nuclear reactors so the moon is going to
be a great source of energy and that's
why there is
this great moon race going on right now
so so that's about
it i know you have lots more questions
but i think i'm gonna stop here
it's been an hour and a half i will be
back tomorrow same time same channel
and i will take up more of your
questions so
thank you very much for all of your
questions i truly
really appreciate it thank you from the
bottom of my heart
and i will continue doing this regularly
i will take up your questions again
tomorrow so that's it for
for today i wish you all a good night a
good day wherever you are
and i will see you tomorrow thank you
bye